What is that old man doing?
那大叔在幹什麼？
-Sir, almost there! -Get back, it's dangerous.
-老師，差不多了！ -退後一點，很危險
Okay, okay!
再來，再下來！
-A little this way! -Okay!
-過來一點！ -好！
-It's heavy!
-好重啊！
Alright, okay!
好啦，搞定！
Sir, how's this?
老師，這樣可以嗎？
-Good. Finish it up. -Alright!
-很好，交給你了！ -沒問題！
What are you doing?! Why are you planting this?
你在做什麼？種這個幹嘛？
I did it for you too.
我以前也這樣為你們做過
A cherry tree?
櫻花？
A Dragon Zakura.
龍櫻
Yeah.
是啊
It's a Dragon Zakura.
是龍櫻
DRAGON ZAKURA
（龍櫻）
The "tatsu" in "Tatsumi" means dragon.
“龍海”中有“龍”字
This Dragon Zakura
這棵龍櫻
will see off future students who get into UTokyo.
將會為未來考上東大的學生們送行
-We've gotta have this! -It brings me back!
-果然不能少了它！ -真是懷念！
Ken!
建先生！
What do you think?
怎麼樣？
Thanks for coming on short notice.
抱歉，謝謝你臨時過來
Anything for you, buddy.
只要是建先生拜託，我很樂意效勞
-I marked the price down. -Thanks a lot.
-我降價了 -多謝啊
-Good-bye! -Thank you!
-再見！ -謝謝！
-What is this? -"Dragon… Zakura"?
-這是什麼？ -“龍…櫻”？
When you four pass,
等你們四個都考上東大的時候
this tree will be in full bloom.
這棵樹剛好也會開滿花
Huh? Did you just say four?
啊？你剛剛說四位？
-Huh? -Hm?
-咦？ -嗯
Huh!?
咦？
You covered for Mr. Sakuragi?
你掩護櫻木老師？
If I were gone,
如果我不在了
he'd lose his chance to try out for UTokyo.
他就會失去上東大的機會
He's always been gunning for UTokyo.
他一直都把東大當目標
-But that was… -Wow, Seto. Way to go.
-但那是… -了不起啊瀨戶，加油！
Iwasaki, aren't you happy? Another friend.
岩崎，高興嗎？又多了個同伴
Yes, I'm happy.
是，我很高興
It's reassuring.
真讓人安心
It's decided.
就這樣決定了
Yay! We got our fourth member.
太好了，有第四位成員了！
Okay everyone, class is starting.
好，大家，課堂要開始啦
-Yes, ma'am. -C'mon!
-是 -走吧！
-That's enough you two! -Okay.
-你們兩位可以停啦！ -好
-Call on us anytime! -Thank you.
-有需要隨時找我們！ -謝謝
See ya.
再見啦
Its metallic luster goes from gold-green to red-bronze.
它的金屬色澤在 金綠色和紅青銅色之間
Its color changes based on the angle. It is nocturnal.
顏色根據角度而變化，夜間活動
-It hides in dead leaves. -This soil is good.
-藏在枯葉中 -這裡的土質很好
So the bugs are healthy.
所以昆蟲也很健康吧？
Ah, carabus insulicola.
啊，淡藍步甲蟲
-Yeah! -Huh.
-對！ -嗯
You'll need an umbrella today.
今天帶把傘比較好
Heavy rain is coming.
要下大雨了
Heavy rain?
大雨？
It'll come at around ten.
大概十點左右吧
-Kenta. -Mari!
-健太 -麻里！
Mari Kosugi?
小杉麻里？
-The top liberal arts student. -I don't care about UTokyo.
-文科的資優生 -我對東大沒興趣
-Let's go, Kenta. -Okay.
-走吧，健太 -好
Why does the UTokyo Special Course have four students?
為什麼東大專科會有四位學生？
-I'm sorry! -If five people get into UTokyo,
-對不起！ -如果有五個人考進東大
I'll have to step down as chairman.
我就得辭去理事長一職
You don't need to worry.
您不用擔心
Those four have among the worst grades in our school.
那四位的成績，是我們學校最差的
For them to get into UTokyo is unthinkable.
他們要考上東大，幾乎不可能
TOP UNIVERSITY COURSE PROPOSAL
（難關大學課程，設立企劃書）
What's this?
這是什麼？
I'm going to crush the UTokyo Special Course with my bare hands.
我會親手毀掉東大專科
We're starting. First off,
好，開始啦，首先
I'll tell you the rules for studying here.
跟各位說明在東大專科學習的規則
Mizuno.
水野
Rule one. Don't tell your parents.
第一條，不要告訴父母
Rule two. If Mr. Sakuragi or I tell you to do something,
第二條，如果 櫻木老師或我讓你們做某件事
even if you don't understand, at least try. That's it.
即使你們不明白 至少要試，就這兩點
How long do I have to keep it from my parents?
我需要隱瞞父母多長時間？
I'll decide the timing and let you know.
我會決定時機，到時再讓你知道
If your parents find out now, they'll just get in the way.
父母現在知情的話，只會阻礙我們
We have to build your foundation for studying first.
我們得先給你們的學習打好基礎
Is that some kind of hellish training?
是什麼地獄特訓嗎？
You think we're living in the past? Mizuno.
現在都什麼時代了？水野
All this?
這全部？
Hang on, this is for junior high.
等一下，這是給國中生的
Of course. None of you know any more than a junior high student.
當然了，你們程度比國中生還差
First know that. You're starting from the basics.
首先明白，你們得從基礎開始
-Really? -I guess so.
-真的？ -我想也是
Do these workbooks, for all subjects, in three weeks.
這些問題本 所有的科目，三週內做完
Three weeks?
三週？
-I guess I could do that. -Do it at least five times.
-我想我可以做到 -至少做五次
-Five? -If you can't, ten laps around the school.
-五次？ -如果做不到，繞著學校跑十圈
It is hellish training!
就是地獄特訓嘛！
And starting today, I'll have things for you to do every day.
還有今天起，我要你們每天做一件事
There's still more?
還要做什麼啦？
Amano, Seto.
天野，瀨戶
Become a YouTuber.
你們兩個當YouTuber
Huh?
什麼？
-A YouTuber? -Hayase, Iwasaki.
-YouTuber？ -早瀨，岩崎
-You two do Twitter. -Twitter?
-妳們兩個負責推特 -推特？
Take your own ordinary life, and tell it to the world in English.
記錄你們的日常生活 然後用英文分享給全世界
Junior high level English is enough.
國中生程度的英文就夠了
Amano, Seto, one video per day.
天野，瀨戶，一天一支影片
Hayase, Iwasaki, your quota is 20 tweets per day.
早瀨，岩崎 妳們的任務是一天20條推文
How dumb. I quit.
好蠢，我退出
Wait!
等一下！
Do what you want.
隨便你
I have no use for a loser who quits without trying.
我對沒試過就放棄的喪家犬沒興趣
Loser?
喪家犬？
I have no reason to go to UTokyo.
我根本沒有去東大的理由！
A reason to go to UTokyo?
去東大的理由？
-You don't need one. -Huh?!
-你不需要 -啊？
-Who could do this without a reason? -How's this for a reason?
-沒有理由，誰會這麼做？ -這個理由怎麼樣？
Go to UTokyo to make a great ramen restaurant.
為了開一家很棒的拉麵店去東大
Are you dissing ramen?
你是在看不起拉麵嗎？
Is there any value in a reason given by someone else?
其他人給的理由，有什麼價值嗎？
If you want a reason to go to UTokyo, find the answer yourself.
如果你想要一個 去東大的理由，自己找答案
But a loser who runs away without trying
但一個還沒嘗試就逃跑的喪家犬
will never do that.
一輩子都辦不到吧
Fine.
好啦
Now we'll measure your current skill
好，我們現在來測試你們的程度
with a junior high review mini-test.
來做一份國中複習小測試
-Ugh. -Clear off your desks.
-呃 -好了，清空你們的桌子
Wow, it's pouring rain.
哇，好大的雨
It was supposed to be sunny.
本來應該放晴的
Ten o'clock?!
十點？
You'll need an umbrella today.
今天帶把傘比較好
Heavy rain is coming.
要下大雨了
It'll come at around ten.
大概十點左右吧
Seriously…
真的假的…
It's as expected.
這是預料中呢
-Seto got a failing score in everything. -I figured.
-瀨戶每一科都不及格 -我想也是
The goal is to pass five students.
我們的目標是讓五位學生考上
We need one more… two if possible.
我們還需要一位 不，可以的話，兩位
I wish someone would come.
真希望有人會來啊
I have a candidate.
我有一位人選
A very smart one.
非常優秀的人選
Are you thinking of Mari Kosugi?
你說的是小杉麻里嗎？
But she…
但她…
Hmm…
嗯…
Wow, so this is the UTokyo Special Course.
哇，這就是東大專科啊
-Fujii… -What's this tent? Hilarious.
-藤井… -這帳篷是怎麼回事？真可笑
Seriously? This is for junior high.
你們是認真的嗎？這是給國中生的
You're at this level. Isn't that bad?
只有這程度，是不是太糟了？
What do you want?
你要幹什麼？
Nothing. I just came to see.
沒事，我只是來看看
And? Which one is your type?
所以呢？哪一個是你的菜？
-Huh? -You joined to get a girl, right?
-什麼？ -你是為了追女生才加入專科的吧？
Everyone's saying that.
大家都這麼說
I joined to get into UTokyo.
我加入是為了上東大
You really think you'll pass? At that level?
你真的覺得你能考上？就憑這水準？
What's his deal? Jerk.
那傢伙是怎樣？好討厭
What are you going on about?
你到底想說什麼？
You must be here for one of those girls too.
你在這裡，也是因為其中一位女生吧
Me?
我？
Uh, no, I'll pass.
不，我就免了
I can't stand dumb girls. I'll catch the dumb.
我受不了笨女生，會被傳染變笨的
Hey.
喂
I do feel sorry for Iwasaki. Her badminton career is over.
但我還蠻同情岩崎的 她的羽球生涯結束了
Her coach ditched her, and now she's snuggling up to Sakuragi.
教練拋棄了她，現在她又來抱著櫻木
It's like, how desperate can you get?
真是，到底是有多飢渴？
-Shut up! -Let me go.
-閉嘴！ -放手！
Seto, Seto, stop it.
瀨戶，停手
What are you doing? Stop!
你們在幹嘛？停手！
Get away, split up.
放手，分開！
Ryo Fujii.
藤井遼
You were there? If you're here, stop the fight!
原來你在啊？ 你在的話應該要阻止他們啊
You'll never get into UTokyo. Give up.
你永遠都上不了東大，放棄吧
If you know about me, you know my grades.
要是你知道我，也該知道我的成績
You caught the flu and could only take Tatsumi's entrance exam.
你得了流感 只能考龍海學園的入學考
Deviation score 68, top in science.
偏差值68，理科資優生
-Aiming for UTokyo Natural Sciences 1. -And you think I'll fail?
-志願是東大理科一類 -而你覺得我會落榜？
I'm calling it.
我敢斷言
A year from now, it won't be you getting into UTokyo.
一年後，考上東大的不會是你
It'll be the UTokyo Special Course students.
而是東大專科的學生們
Wow. Shall we have a contest?
是喔，我們要不要來場比賽？
I don't think they could score half the points I could.
我不認為他們能考到我一半的分數
Sure.
好啊
Let's do it.
來吧
I hear you're having a contest with Fujii.
我聽說你要和藤井比賽
I'll stand witness to this contest.
我要來當這比賽的見證人
As you like.
隨妳意
If Fujii wins,
要是藤井贏了
the UTokyo Special Course disbands.
東大專科就解散
-What? -If we don't go all in, it's boring, no?
-什麼？ -不賭上全部也太無聊了，不是嗎？
-If it's disbanded, we would be… -Fired, I assume.
-要是解散專科，我們就會… -被開除吧
But, what about the students?
那學生們怎麼辦？
The students aiming for UTokyo.
那些學生的目標是東大
I'll take them in.
我會接手他們
-Huh? -Our school has established a new course.
-啊？ -我們學校這次開辦了一門新課程
"Top Uni Course"?
“難關大課程？”
Weren't you against becoming a high-level school?
當初妳不是反對我們 轉型成升學學校嗎？
The chairman's educational philosophy is to respect students' freedom.
理事長的教育理念是尊重學生的自由
Not only UTokyo, if they want to aim high,
不只是東大，如果學生有更大的目標
we will respond to those needs.
我們也會臨機應變，滿足這些需求
By the way, Fujii says he's joining the Top Uni Course.
話說，藤井說他會加入難關大課程
Well? Will you do it?
怎麼樣？你是賭
Or won't you?
還是不賭？
Of course not.
當然不賭啊
-We'll do it. -Huh?
-我們賭 -啊？
The contest is in three weeks.
比賽在三週後
Fujii's score and our students' average score.
藤井的分數和專科學生們的平均分
The higher score wins.
誰比較高，誰就贏
Exam questions from old UTokyo exams.
考題從東大的歷年試題中
The chairman, Mizuno, the Top Uni Course teacher and I.
由理事長、水野 難關大課程的教師和我
We will discuss and decide.
我們四人來討論決定
Alright.
好
The loser's class will be eliminated.
輸家的課程將被廢除
What are you saying? We won't! We won't do it!
你在說什麼？我們不參加！
Why did you accept such a contest?
你怎麼會接受這樣的比賽？
The science top? We'll never win.
理科資優生？我們不可能贏的
We'll be fired and homeless. What are you doing?
我們會被開除 然後無家可歸，你到底在幹嘛？
Why are you so worried? Did you forget?
妳怎麼那麼慌張？妳忘了嗎？
-Huh? -You were a loser through and through.
-什麼？ -妳曾經是個徹徹底底的喪家犬
Remember how you got out of it?
還記得妳是怎麼擺脫的嗎？
We destroy the inferiority complexes they've given themselves.
這是打破他們加在自己身上的自卑感
-We'll never have such a chance. -But what if we lose?
-再好不過的機會了！ -但要是我們輸了呢？
What will be, will be.
那就到時候再說吧
-More like, we'll be bankrupt! -Oh yeah.
-到那時我們就破產了！ -啊，對了
Right.
這個
TOYAMA LANDSCAPING
（遠山景觀）
CHERRY BLOSSOM TREE
（櫻花樹）
Three hundred thousand…
三十萬…
That bastard…
那混帳…
I can't! Never, never!
辦不到，絕對辦不到！
-Be for real. -If we lose, the course is gone?
-別開玩笑了 -要是我們輸了，專科就完了？
That's going too far.
這打賭也太過分了吧
What, don't you want to win?
幹嘛，你們不想贏嗎？
You're going to let Fujii mock you?
你們就這樣讓藤井嘲笑？
Of course not.
怎麼可能
There's a chance we could win?
但你認為我們有機會贏，對吧？
That…
那…
depends on you guys.
要看你們
Why did you say yes?
那為什麼你要答應？
A fun game like this?
這麼好玩的遊戲
How could I miss out?
我怎麼能錯過呢？
C'mon, don't do this for fun.
拜託，不要為了好玩答應這種事
Don't worry.
別擔心
There are ways.
有好幾種方法
Number one…
第一個方法
That would be…
那就是…
What?
什麼？
-This. -Huh?
-這個 -啊？
We already heard that.
這個我們都已經聽過啦
Solve problems, read explanations, and study.
解題，讀解釋，然後學習
If you still don't get it,
如果還不明白
teach each other.
就互相教導
Teach each other?
互相教導？
Amano, you teach math. Hayase, literature.
天野，你教數學，早瀨，文學
Iwasaki, your English was highest.
岩崎，妳的英文分數最高
-Seto. -Yes!
-瀨戶 -是！
You're bad at everything.
你全部都很差
I know that.
我知道啦
But idiots teaching other idiots? What's the point?
但笨蛋教笨蛋，有意義嗎？
That's it. You said something good.
就是這個，你說到重點了
There are advantages to being idiots.
當笨蛋是有一些好處的
If you're with someone who knows a little more,
既然對方只比你多懂一點
your brain decides that you can do it too.
你的大腦會覺得，你也可以做到
Plus, the one teaching gets to organize their knowledge,
而且，教學的人也可以整理知識
unclear parts become clear, and their degree of understanding goes up.
不清楚的部分變得清楚 理解程度也會變高
-Huh. -Wow.
-哦 -哇
Number two. Have you started YouTube and Twitter yet?
第二，你們開始 用YouTube和推特了嗎？
Well…
這個嘛…
People who move slowly miss opportunities.
行動緩慢的人，會錯失機會
Especially Amano.
特別是天野
Don't think, just do it.
別想太多了，去做
-Uh, okay. -And number three.
-呃，好 -還有第三
Before school in the morning, and after school,
上課前的早上還有下課後
you'll get a problem from Mizuno.
水野會給你們一道問題
A problem? What do you mean?
問題？什麼意思？
You'll understand eventually.
妳最後會明白的
Right?
對吧？
I see…
原來如此
Listen.
聽我說
While you're here worrying, Fujii is getting smarter.
當你們在這拖拖拉拉時 藤井正在變得更聰明
We have three weeks.
距離比賽還有三週
How you spend that time is up to you guys.
怎麼運用這時間，全看你們了
-Okay. -Yes, sir.
-好吧 -好
Yes, sir.
好
That's what YouTubers do, right?
YouTuber 都是這麼做的，對吧？
UTOKYO SPECIAL COURSE
（東大專科）
What is a three-day monk? Explain in one sentence.
三分鐘熱度是什麼意思？ 請用一句話解釋
A quiz?
常識問答？
-Thank you for waiting. -A three-day monk…
-久等了 -三分鐘熱度…
That's Hayase.
就是早瀨吧
Hey! Well, I thought so too.
喂！雖然我也這麼覺得啦
Three-day monk…
三分鐘熱度…
"Giving up easily," I guess?
是“輕易放棄”的意思嗎？
Why is she asking this?
她為什麼問這個？
Where are most pumpkins sold in Japan produced?
日本市面的南瓜大多產自哪裡？
Hokkaido?
北海道？
Mexico?
墨西哥？
Mine is from New Zealand.
我的來自紐西蘭
MINE IS FROM NEW ZEALAND.
（我的來自紐西蘭）
Why do you think most pumpkins come from those places?
為什麼大多數南瓜來自這些地區？
Why?
為什麼？
How would I know?
我怎麼知道？
Um, "I have good…"
呃，“我有好…”
Do I need an "a"?
我該不該加“個”？
"I have a good day today."
“我今天有個愉快的一天”
Is "have" right?
加“有”對嗎？
Good enough. Eighteen tweets to go.
隨便啦，還剩十八個推文
I have to do that too.
我還得寫這些
I don't have time for a quiz.
哪有時間做常識問答啦
Red sky in morning, sailors take warning. Red sky at night, sailor's delight. Why?
“朝紅雨，夕紅晴”，是為什麼？
That's just a proverb.
就只是句諺語啊
Watch it.
看路啊
Everyone, did you think about the problems?
大家有想過那些問題的答案嗎？
I did think about them…
是有想了一下…
First, the pumpkin-producing regions problem.
首先是南瓜產地的問題
In addition to Hokkaido, there were Mexico and New Zealand.
除了北海道，還有墨西哥和紐西蘭
Why are those three areas common?
為什麼是這三個地區呢？
Hokkaido is cold, Mexico is hot. I couldn't find anything in common.
北海道冷，墨西哥熱 我完全找不到共通點
When are pumpkins in season anyway?
話說，南瓜季節在什麼時候？
Summer? No, it's winter.
夏天？不，是冬天
Hayase, what's wrong?
早瀨，怎麼了？
Is there any point to this?
討論這些有什麼意義嗎？
What are you saying?
為什麼要問這個？
Why are we doing all these nonsense quizzes?
為什麼要我們 做這些愚蠢的常識問答？
Fujii is way ahead of us.
藤井現在遠遠超過我們
He had a huge English notebook full of sticky notes.
他有一大本滿滿都是 便利貼的英語筆記本
There's no time before the contest.
我們離比賽沒多少時間了
If everyone has time to talk about pumpkins,
大家有時間討論南瓜
we could be memorizing English words.
還不如拿來記英語單字
Okay, let me ask you.
好，那我問妳
How do you memorize those words?
妳怎麼記那些單字？
Say them out loud, or write them over and over?
把它們念出來，或者重複寫？
Classic exam failing method.
典型的失敗考試法
So what should I do?
不然應該怎麼做？
Smart people have good memories.
本來聰明的人記憶力就很強
We can't win.
怎麼可能贏的了？
You're wrong.
妳錯了
Having a good memory
記憶力這種東西
doesn't make much of a difference, save for some unique people.
除了少數特別的人外 大多數人都沒什麼差別
In UTokyo, 80% of the students have the same memory as you.
在東大，八成的學生記憶力和妳一樣
Really?
真的嗎？
Then why…
那為什麼…
-There are tricks to remembering. -Tricks?
-記憶是有技巧的 -技巧？
For example…
比如說…
What does this word mean?
-這個詞是什麼意思？ -“Unite”
-I think it means to get together? -Yes.
-我想是“團結”的意思 -對
Okay, here's a question.
好，那問題來了
Why does "unite" mean "get together"?
為什麼“unite” 的意思 是“團結”？
Why?
為什麼？
Because somebody decided that's what the word was?
因為某個人決定了 這個詞就該是這個意思吧？
By some important person a long time ago?
很久以前，某個很偉大的人規定的？
You can't think like that.
妳不能這樣思考
Hayase, what kind of ability do you think UTokyo wants the most?
早瀨，妳覺得東大最想要什麼能力？
Um…
呃…
Knowing lots of difficult things?
能懂得很多困難的事？
No. How well you can consider the substance of things.
錯，是思考事物本質的能力
That's it.
是這個
Substance?
本質？
In this case,
以這為例
I would first look up the origin of the word "unite."
我會先查一查 “unite”這個詞的詞源
And then…
然後…
I would learn that "uni" means "one."
我會發現“uni”的意思是“一”
Making something one is "unite," which is why it means "get together."
“Unite”的意思是 統一某些事情，也就是“團結”
It can also mean "combine," "link" and "marry."
它也可以是 “結合”、“聯合”、“結婚”
Another meaning is, "possess in combination."
還有個意思是“兩者兼具”
If you consider they all come from the word meaning "one" it's easy to remember.
如果知道它們都來自“一”這個意思 就很容易記住了
Yeah it is…
是呢…
There are many other "uni" words.
還有很多“uni”衍生的詞
Tell me what you think of.
告訴我妳想到什麼
Uni…
Uni…
-Uniform! -Yes.
-制服！ -對
So why is "uni" used there?
那為什麼這裡會用到“uni”呢？
Because a team all wears the same clothing.
因為一群人都穿一樣的服裝
-That's right. -Yay!
-沒錯！ -耶！
Anything else?
還有什麼嗎？
At a university, you can learn many things in one place?
大學，因為你能在一個地方 學到很多東西？
Good. Keep it up. Hayase?
很好，繼續，早瀨
Um… uni… unicorn!
呃…獨角獸！
-Because they have one horn? -That's right!
-因為牠們只有一個角？ -對！
Seto?
瀨戶？
Uni…
Uni…
Uniqlo.
優衣庫
That's a brand name.
那是品牌名字
It's not even English.
連英文都不是啦
Uniqlo's name comes from "Unique Clothing Warehouse."
優衣庫的名字來自 “獨特的服裝倉庫”
"Unique" means "one individual, unlike others"
“Unique”的意思是 “獨特，和其他人不同”
so you're barely right.
所以勉強算是答對了
Oh, unique.
哦，獨特
I think I could remember that easily.
的確這樣很容易就記住了
-Yeah. -Listen.
-嗯 -聽著
UTokyo students think "Why?" about everything they see.
東大生看到一切 都會去想“為什麼”
They try to see the substance.
他們試著去看本質
What you must do is copy that way of thinking.
你們需要的是仿效這種思考模式
By the way, those problems you think are quizzes?
順帶一提，那些你們 以為是常識問答的問題
They're all questions from past UTokyo entrance exams.
它們都是過去東大入學的考題
Seriously?
真的嗎？
In UTokyo exams, you might have to add a punchline to a comic strip.
在東大入學考中 考生可能要為四格漫畫想結尾
Or in "Janken Glico," which makes you win more,
或找出“格力高猜拳”中 哪個勝算更大
rock, paper, or scissors.
是石頭、布或剪刀？
These have all been questions.
這些都曾是考題
UTokyo has a lot of questions based on daily life.
東大有很多基於日常生活的考題
-Wow. -So that pumpkin one…
-哇 -所以南瓜那一題…
That was a geography question from 2015.
那是2015年的地理題
"Many pumpkins are imported from Mexico and New Zealand. Explain why."
“許多南瓜進口自 墨西哥和紐西蘭，請解釋原因”
By the way, pumpkins are in season in summer and autumn.
話說回來，南瓜季節在夏天和秋天
Think about that. Well?
從這點想的話，能明白嗎？
I get it. In Japan, they're only available in summer and autumn
原來如此，在日本的話 只有夏天和秋天可以收成
but Mexico is warm year-round.
但墨西哥常年溫暖
When it's winter in Japan, it's summer in New Zealand!
日本冬天的時候，紐西蘭是夏天！
-That's it. -Wow!
-就是這樣！ -好厲害！
We solved a UTokyo question!
我們解開了一道東大的題目！
Do you get it, Hayase? That's why you can't think "It's always been that way."
早瀨，妳明白了嗎？這就是為什麼 妳不能認為“事情一直都是這樣”
Everything has meaning. Substance.
每一件事都有它的意義，本質
Why is the question written that way?
為什麼問題這麼問？
Why are we making you do things that seem like games?
為什麼我們要做 這些遊戲一樣的事情？
See it from every angle to get the substance.
從不同的角度去看，去尋找本質
I guess I'll get serious about Twitter.
我想我得認真發推特了
That reminds me, Amano, your video was funny.
對了，說到這個 天野，你的影片真搞笑
Yeah, that was awesome.
嗯，真的很棒！
Like this, right?
這樣，對嗎？
Uh… I guess.
呃…是這樣嗎？
-Seto, you're not doing YouTube? -Why would I?
-瀨戶，你不做YouTube嗎？ -誰要做啊？
Do it!
做啊！
How many students joined the Top Uni Course?
有多少學生加入難關大課程了？
At this moment…
直到現在
Just one, Ryo Fujii.
只有一位，藤井遼
Why?
為什麼？
Actually…
其實…
Tomorrow, the Top Uni Course classes will begin.
明天，難關大課程就要開課了
If you want to join, talk to me.
想參與的同學，請來找我
I'll be in charge of it.
我是負責人
Hey, Fujii. See you tomorrow.
藤井，明天見
Mr. Oyama.
大山老師
Where did you graduate from?
你的母校是哪所學校？
-Huh? -Heisei School of Education.
-啊？ -平成教育大學
A third-rate school.
是間三流學校呢
Why do I have to be taught by someone with a lower deviation score?
我為什麼要讓 偏差值比我低的人來指導我？
I signed up for the Top Uni Course because the chairman asked me to.
我會報名難關大課程 是因為理事長邀請我
But I have no intention of taking classes. Good-bye.
但我沒打算去上課，再見
-Hey… -Third rate!
-嘿… -三流！
Third rate, third rate!
三流！
Good grief. That Fujii is such a jerk.
可惡，那個藤井真是討人厭
That's why I'm against becoming a high-level school.
所以我才反對成為升學學校
Studying all the time makes people stupid and heartless.
成天念書會讓人 變得又笨又沒有同理心
You are so right.
您說得對
Well, as long as he wins the contest, that's fine.
無論如何，他只要贏了比賽就好
Then we can destroy the UTokyo Special Course.
那我們就能毀掉東大專科了
Hey, Kaede. I don't get this.
楓，我不明白這個
This "party" means a political party.
這裡的“party”是政黨的意思
Politics? That's not a party at all.
政黨？這和派對完全沒有關係
-I'll look up the origin. -Okay.
-我去查一查詞源 -好
Um, "part."
這個嘛，“part”
It looks like it came from "portion."
好像是“部分”的意思
A party is where a number of people get together and have fun.
派對是一群人聚在一起玩樂的地方
A political party is people with the same beliefs coming together.
政黨則是相同 理念的人聚在一起的地方
When you put it like that, it makes sense.
這樣想的話我就明白了
-Thanks. -Yeah.
-謝謝 -嗯
Hang on. This one too.
等一下，還有這個
Which one?
哪個？
POLITICAL PARTY
（政黨）
Seto, are those flashcards?
瀨戶，那是單字卡嗎？
-Great! -I guess.
-很棒！ -大概吧
By month, at representative points on the Pacific side…
每月來看，太平洋這側的代表地點…
-Another beer. -Yes, sir!
-再來一瓶啤酒 -好
Oh, shadows.
哦，影子啊
-"Bottle." -What's up?
-“Bottle” -幹什麼？
Are you studying? What's gotten into you?
你在念書嗎？發生了什麼事？
No, it's nothing.
沒有啦
Give this to Mr. Sakuragi.
把這個交給櫻木老師
-Huh? Okay. -Hurry.
-啊？好 -快點
-Here. -Uh-huh.
-請用 -嗯
This is Setoya.
瀨戶家你好
Sorry, could you wait a little longer?
對不起，你能再等一下嗎？
I'm sorry. I'm trying to collect it now.
非常抱歉，我正在籌錢了
I'm sorry.
對不起
ONE DAY BEFORE THE CONTEST
（比賽前一天）
Here are the results of today's mini-test.
這是今天小測驗的結果
Mizuno.
水野
Amano, from a total of 500, 400.
天野，滿分500中，拿到400分
It went up.
進步了
Hayase, 380 points.
早瀨，380分
-Yay! -Iwasaki, 420 points.
-太好了！ -岩井，420分
-Yes! -Seto, 270 points.
-耶！ -瀨戶，270分
Everyone has gotten much better in a short period. Well done.
大家在短時間內 都進步了很多，你們做得很好
Isn't that great? We might really win!
這不是很好嗎？我們可能真的會贏！
-Seto, you improved a lot. -Yeah.
-瀨戶，你進步了很多 -嗯
Seto, you worked hard.
瀨戶，你很努力呢
You can be happy. I know you feel the difference.
你就老實開心一點嘛 明明你也知道和以前的差距
Shut up.
吵死了
Honestly, it'll be hard.
老實說，很難
I can't say that to them though.
但我不能告訴他們
Everyone's working hard, but they're finally at junior high level.
大家都很努力 但他們才終於達到國中程度
Can they win?
要說能不能贏
It will depend on the type of questions.
只能看考題的類型了
If it's physics, they'll be clobbered.
如果是物理，肯定會被擊敗
Especially Seto. Are you listening?
特別是瀨戶，你在聽嗎？
We took past UTokyo exams from the last 20 years
我們從過去二十年的東大考題
and chose possible questions for each subject.
為每一科選了一些預備考題
Okay, now we just have to select the questions.
我知道了，那接下來 只需要決定出哪些題目了
I have a proposal, Chairman.
我有個建議，理事長
I'd like you to choose the questions for the test.
我希望由妳來為考試選題
Me?
我？
Bottle.
瓶子
Care.
照顧
Oh, it's climate.
啊，是氣候
-Hey! -Hah, "unique"?
-喂！ -哈，“unique”？
Don't you know that?
這不需要特別去記吧？
Give it.
還給我
I feel sorry for the Special Course kids.
我真可憐東大專科的孩子們
They'd have better chances without you around.
沒了你，他們搞不好有機會贏
You don't even feel bad?
你就不會覺得愧疚嗎？
You're holding them back. Catch on!
你在拖他們後腿，明白嗎？
Or are you too dumb?
還是你太笨了？
If you lose, those teachers will be fired, right?
要是你輸了 那些老師也會被開除，對吧？
If it were me, I'd stand down.
我如果是你，我就會退出了
SPECIAL EXAM UTOKYO SPECIAL COURSE VS FUJII RYO
（特別考試，東大專科對藤井遼）
Where's Seto?
瀨戶怎麼了？
Maybe he's running late.
他可能遲到了吧
He probably just ran away.
說不定逃走了吧？
Huh? He wouldn't do that.
什麼？怎麼可能
He's worked so hard.
他那麼努力到現在
Thanks for waiting. Is everyone here?
久等了，大家都到了嗎？
Ma'am, not everyone.
老師，還沒到齊
Oh, Seto called and said he'd be away today.
哦，瀨戶剛剛打來電話 說他今天不會來
-Huh? -Good for you guys!
-啊？ -這對你們來說是好消息啊！
He'd hold you back if he was here.
他要是在，肯定會拖你們後腿
Shut up!
閉嘴！
We still have five minutes, right?
老師，我們還有五分鐘，對吧？
Hang on!
等一下！
You don't have to count Seto's score.
不算瀨戶的分數沒關係啦
I need a little handicap, otherwise it's boring.
我需要讓一點分數，要不然太無聊了
The person you are trying to reach is…
您所撥打的號碼暫時…
What are you doing, Seto? I hope he didn't really run away…
瀨戶到底在幹嘛？ 他該不是真的逃走了吧？
He's not that kind of guy.
他不是那種人
Look, I found this.
看，我找到這個
He's not showing his face, but that voice…
他沒有露臉，但那聲音…
-Seto? -Why isn't he here?
-瀨戶？ -他為什麼不來呢？
He worked so hard.
他那麼努力
It's time.
時間到了
But Seto's not here yet.
但瀨戶還沒來
Forget about Seto.
忘了瀨戶吧
How could you say that?
你怎麼可以這麼說？
Are you confident enough to worry about another person?
你們還有空閒去擔心別人嗎？
Or have you given up from the start?
還是你們一開始就已經放棄了？
-No! -Then focus on yourself.
-才不是！ -那就專注在自己身上吧
I told you.
我跟你們說過了
I'd help you win,
我會幫你們贏的
so you believed me, and did what you could.
你們相信了我，盡了力
You'd throw that away?
你們要白費這些努力嗎？
In an exam,
在考試中
you never know what will happen. Entrance exams are the same.
你們永遠不知道 會發生什麼事，入學考也一樣
That day, at that time, no matter the conditions,
那天，那個時刻，無論什麼情況
you only have one chance.
機會只有一次
All you can do now
你們現在唯一能做的
is focus on yourself. That's it.
只有專注在自己身上，就是這樣
MISSED CALLS IWASAKI, HAYASE, AMANO
（未接來電）
I'll clean up. You go to school.
我來清理，你快去學校吧
Now is not the time for that.
現在不是管學校的時候
Thank you.
謝謝
The test is worth 20 points. You will have twenty minutes.
這張試卷滿分二十分 答題時間現在起二十分鐘
Now, begin.
現在，開始
An English essay and geography question.
英語作文和地理題
What is this map?
這地圖是什麼？
It looks hard.
看起來很難
How can I answer this?
糟糕，我該怎麼答呢？
Fujii is writing a lot.
藤井已經寫了很多
What could he be writing?
他都寫了什麼？
Calm down. Focus on yourself.
冷靜，專注在自己身上
Right. Don't forget to think.
對了，別忘記思考
Substance. Think about the substance.
本質，想想本質
Oh, that's what this question is asking…
這樣啊，原來這題想問的是…
Time's up.
時間到
Let me through.
借過一下
Sorry.
不好意思
-Let me through. -Sorry.
-借過 -抱歉
Pardon me.
不好意思
I will present the results.
我現在將公布成績
Amano, 14 points.
天野，14分
Hayase, 13 points.
早瀨，13分
Iwasaki, 15 points.
岩崎，15分
Fujii,
藤井
11 points.
11分
Y-Yay!
啊，太好了！
Really? We won?
真的？我們贏了？
We won!
我們贏了！
No way!
騙人！
Yay!
太好了！
Mr. Sakuragi really is amazing.
櫻木老師果然很厲害
How lame, Fujii. You lost to the Special Course.
好遜，藤井，你輸給了專科
You're kidding! How could I lose? Give it!
開玩笑！我怎麼可能輸？給我！
There must be a mistake with the marking.
一定是批改錯了
Re-do it, third-rate school!
給我重批，三流大學！
Nope, there's nothing wrong with the marking.
不，批改沒什麼問題
What's wrong is your answers.
問題就在你的答案
Show this idiot, Mizuno.
水野，教教這個笨蛋吧
Idiot?
笨蛋？
First, the English question.
首先，第一題英語題
What would happen if you could read other's thoughts?
要是你能讀懂 其他人的想法，會發生什麼事？
That was the question.
這是考題
Read your answer.
把你的答案念出來
It's long.
太長了
I don't know what you're saying.
我不知道你在寫什麼
You do know. If people could read minds, they can't lie, so peace would come.
看的懂吧？要是每個人都懂讀心術 他們就無法說謊，世界就會和平
-That's obvious. -I see. Now I understand.
-很明顯吧！ -這樣啊，現在我明白了
You didn't write that people couldn't lie. You didn't explain that.
你沒寫人們無法說謊，你沒解釋這個
It wasn't logical and on top of that, you used too many hard words and phrases.
它不合邏輯 而且你用了太多複雜的詞彙
So you had a lot of spelling mistakes.
也因此犯了很多拼寫錯誤
What did you guys write?
你們寫了什麼？
Amano.
天野
Yes, sir.
是
That's good. Hayase?
很好，早瀨
-Good. Iwasaki? -Yes, sir.
-好，岩崎 -是
-Good. -Simple and easy to understand.
-很好 -簡單易懂
It's easy English, with no spelling errors.
這是簡單的英語，沒有任何拼寫錯誤
No way.
開玩笑吧
Compared to a complicated answer,
比起複雜的答案
answering simply is actually more difficult.
簡單地回答其實更難
But in the real world, it's a skill you'll need your whole life.
但在出了社會後 這是一輩子都需要的技能
Discussing things every day, and teaching one another.
每天討論，互相教導
Always valuing communication.
重視溝通
That was to build this skill. YouTube and Twitter, too.
都是為了培養這項技能 YouTube和推特也是一樣
So that's why.
原來如此
Next is the geography question.
下一題是地理題
What it is really asking is if you can imagine how people feel.
這題真正要問的 是你能不能想像人們的感受
How people feel?
人們的感受？
Fujii,
藤井
you only answered from the administrative perspective.
你只從行政角度回答了問題
There was nothing about the citizens' perspective
缺乏了市民的角度
so you only got half the points.
所以你只得了一半的分數
You clearly chose these questions to give the Special Course the advantage!
你們很明顯是選了 對專科有優勢的考題吧！
That's not true.
這可不對
The questions were chosen by the chairman.
這些考題都是理事長選的
But that's…
但那是…
I have a proposal, Chairman.
我有個建議，理事長
I'd like you to choose the questions for the test.
我希望由妳來為考試選題
Me?
我？
You, more than anyone, have noble principles towards education.
妳對於教育有比任何人都崇高的理念
I'm sure the questions you choose will follow those principles.
即使妳只選一題，也會貫徹這些理念
Something to bring awareness to the students.
能激發學生思考的問題
-Am I wrong? -You're very right.
-我說錯了嗎？ -你說得很對
For example, Mr. Oyama's questions.
比如說，大山老師選的考題
They're mostly asking about esoteric knowledge.
大多都是難解的問題
But cramming in knowledge isn't what matters in life.
但人生中最重要的不是塞滿知識
Having a rich life matters.
而是活得豐富
Ah, I see.
哦，原來如此
This geography question Mizuno chose.
水野老師選的這道地理題
This will encourage a broad perspective and critical thinking.
能激發更廣闊的視角和批判性思考
This English question is very practical.
英語題也很實用
You tricked me.
你設計我
You led me to choose them with your clever words.
你用花言巧語誤導我選擇這些考題
So what? They're all real UTokyo questions.
那又怎樣？這些確實是東大的考題
Fujii should have solved them with ease.
藤井應該能很輕鬆地解答
That's why you chose them, no?
妳也是這樣想才選這些題目的吧？
Fujii, you didn't lose because of the questions.
藤井，你的敗因不是因為考題
It was your nasty personality.
而是因為你那爛性格
My personality?
性格？
That's unrelated to the exam.
那和考試沒有關係
You look down on people and reject help even from teachers.
你看不起人，拒絕老師們的協助
You've studied all on your own.
只靠自己埋頭苦讀
But you have a weakness.
但你的失分
If you had taken advice, you could've avoided this.
要是你肯聽取意見，就可以輕鬆避免
UTokyo often has questions that require multiple perspectives.
東大經常會出需要多角度思考的考題
You need to be able to imagine how different people feel.
也就是說，你得設身處地 想像不同人的感受
It's a message from UTokyo about who they want.
東大透過這些考題 傳達出他們想要這樣的人
People who kick down others
那些貶低身邊的人
and try to climb up alone are not what UTokyo wants.
只想獨自向上的人，不是東大要的人
That's why I said you'll never get into UTokyo, Fujii.
所以我之前才說 你是不可能考上東大的，藤井
People like you?
像你這樣的人
UTokyo doesn't need you, nor does society.
東大不需要你，社會也不需要
Know that.
認清這點吧
That's bullshit.
開什麼玩笑
Serves you right.
活該
Fujii, why not give up on UTokyo?
藤井，要不你放棄東大吧？
Cut it out, you guys. Go back to class.
好了你們，回教室去
All of you are idiots.
你們全都是笨蛋
-Keep laughing. -Huh? What did you say?
-儘管笑吧 -啊？你說什麼？
Don't get high and mighty.
少囂張了
You're idiots who only feel superior when beating someone down.
你們是只有在打擊別人時 才會感到優越的笨蛋
-What gives? -You're just saying "idiot" over and over.
-你說什麼？ -只會重複“笨蛋”，吵死了
I call them as I see them.
把笨蛋叫笨蛋有什麼問題？
Compared to you, Fujii's twisted spirit is a hundred times better.
跟你們相比 藤井扭曲的靈魂還好幾百倍
He chose UTokyo, and he's working in his own way.
他決定要考東大 以他自己的方式在努力著
Hey, old man.
喂，老頭
Come outside.
出來
Stop!
停手！
What do you think you are doing?!
你打算對學生們幹什麼？
Uh, no, I, uh…
呃，我…
Enough of this nonsense!
夠了，別再胡鬧了
I can't allow you to insult students in front of me.
我不能允許你在我面前羞辱學生
They're not insults. This is kindness.
這不是羞辱，這是好意
You…
你…
Shall I tell you why you're idiots?
要我說說為什麼你們是笨蛋嗎？
This is why.
因為
You don't know anything.
你們什麼都不懂
I'm not talking about textbook knowledge.
我不是說課本上的知識
You don't know the reality and structure of the world.
而是你們不瞭解社會的現狀和結構
-Give it up. -Hey.
-說夠了沒？ -喂
-Gimme a break. -Don't mock the students!
-開什麼玩笑 -不要嘲笑學生！
Do you know what's happening in the world now?
你們知道世界正發生什麼事嗎？
Unprecedented crises.
前所未有的危機
Epidemics. Natural disasters.
疾病，天災
Leading to economic paralysis.
連帶經濟癱瘓
Unimaginable things are happening, one after another.
無法想像的事正一件一件發生
A war could even break out.
甚至可能會爆發戰爭
What are you saying?
你到底在說什麼？
What was common sense doesn't fly anymore.
曾經的常識不再適用了
Absolutely anything could happen.
什麼事情都可能發生
When that happens, this country where you all live…
到那個時候，你們生活著的這個國家
What does it need the most? Do you know?
它最需要什麼？你們知道嗎？
How would I know?
我怎麼會知道？
Money.
錢
Taxes.
稅金
This country wants you all to stay idiots. That's the truth.
這個國家想讓你們 一個個繼續當笨蛋，這是真相
Without any doubts.
什麼都不懷疑
Without knowing anything, without looking up anything.
什麼都不知道，什麼都不去查
Just following the system, continuing to work,
只會一味跟隨制度，持續工作
and paying money. That's the citizens they want.
然後繳稅，這就是他們想要的國民
How would you reword that?
換句話說，這是什麼？
You there.
你，那位
Kohashi. Iwai.
小橋，岩井
Huh?
什麼？
Diligence?
勤奮？
Close.
很接近
A workhorse.
拉車馬
This country wants you to shut up and pull the carriage.
這國家要你們閉嘴去拉車
They want workhorses. That's easier for them.
他們要拉車馬 這對他們來說更好駕馭
"The world is fair. The citizens are free. There is no discrimination."
“世界是平等的 國民是自由的，不存在歧視”
We're told this.
我們被這樣灌輸著
But reality is different.
但現實並非如此
No matter how hard you work, no matter how you muster your strength.
無論你多努力，無論你怎麼竭盡力氣
If you can't see the substance,
如果你看不到本質
you can't even stand in the ring with authority.
你甚至無法和當權者站在同個擂台上
So what?
那又怎麼樣？
That's the government's fault.
那是國家的錯
We've got nothing to do with it.
不關我們的事
That's why you're idiots.
所以說你們是笨蛋
It's someone's fault, the nation's fault, the era's fault. Criticizing others.
別人的錯、國家的錯、時代的錯 去指責其他人
What changes by complaining?
抱怨能改變什麼？
It suits the ones who make the rules. That's why they made this system.
那些制定規則的人正是想要這樣 所以他們創造出了這個制度
If you say you've got nothing to do with it,
一直說這和自己沒關係
you'll spend your life being tricked and paying money.
你的一生都會被蒙在鼓裡，不停繳錢
Why is society like this?
為什麼社會是這個樣子？
Who made it this way, for what reason?
是誰做的？為什麼讓它變成這樣？
Learn how to see the substance, and find your own answer.
學會看見本質的方法 然後尋找屬於你的答案
Then finally
在這之後
a workhorse can become a human.
拉車馬才能變成人
To get there, studying is the only way.
若要如此，念書是唯一的路徑
Studying
念書
is the only equality this country allows.
是這個國家唯一允許的平等
Right now, you're lucky.
現在你們很幸運
Now you've got me.
現在你們有我
No matter how stupid and lazy you are,
不管你有多笨多懶惰
if you want it, I can get you into UTokyo.
只要你想要，我可以把你送進東大
You get it? If you want to be more than just exploited.
聽好了，如果你不想要被剝削
If you don't want a life of discontent.
如果你不想過一個滿腹怨言的人生
You've got to study!
你就得念書！
Ugly and stupid can go to UTokyo!
笨蛋和醜女都給我上東大！
There he goes.
出現了
Please don't plant biased ideas in my students.
請不要給我的學生灌輸這種刻板印象
Everyone, back to class.
大家都回教室去
-Break it up. -Back to class.
-好，解散 -回教室了
Break it up.
解散
Hey, Fujii.
喂，藤井
You're welcome to join us anytime.
如果你想參加東大專科，隨時過來
I'll fix your spirit.
我會修補好你的靈魂
Why would I?
誰要去啊？
We've managed to save our jobs.
我們成功保住了工作
But we have to get five students to pass.
但還是得讓五位學生考上
Didn't you say you had a smart candidate?
你不是說你有個優秀的人選嗎？
They'll come eventually.
遲早會來的
This is a stag beetle. A giant stag beetle.
這是鍬蟲，巨鍬甲蟲
It's a rare variety. It has a huge jaw.
是罕見的品種，有巨大的顎
Time to go home, Kenta.
該回家了，健太
Mari.
麻里
Here.
給你
-Let's go. -Yeah.
-走吧 -嗯
I'm going to Setoya now. Do you…
我現在要去瀨戶家，你要一起…
No. Don't go to Setoya for a while.
不行，這陣子別去瀨戶家
But I'm worried about Seto.
但我擔心瀨戶
Leave him.
不要管他
Hang on, sir.
莫非老師
Do you know something?
你知道些什麼？
He who masters IT, masters the exam!
誰掌握了資訊技術，就掌握了考試！
Use Study Sapuri to root out your weaknesses.
用學習補品，把你們的弱點連根拔起
Study with these "idiot" headbands.
戴著這些“笨蛋”頭巾學習
Idiots!
笨蛋！
Are you toying with our children?
你是在玩弄我們的孩子嗎？
Ten Family Rules for UTokyo.
“東大合格必勝法，十大家庭條規”
Your children can definitely get into UTokyo.
妳們的孩子絕對可以考上東大
-Is that you, Mizuno? -Yes, sir.
-是妳嗎，水野？ -是的
Cramming is true education.
塞滿知識才是真正的教育！
This is the Spartan you wanted.
這就是你們需要的斯巴達教學
I'll accept no less than 100%.
-我只接受滿分的成績 -什麼？
I have a bad feeling about this…
我有種不祥的預感…
If you're good at elementary math, you'll be able to study.
要是你擅長小學二年級數學 你就有學習的能力
I'll deal with our debt somehow.
債務的事我會想辦法處理的
I'll drop out and work.
我會休學，然後去工作
I'm an idiot anyway.
反正我是笨蛋
So you're giving up on UTokyo?
那你要放棄東大了嗎？
This is my problem.
這是我的問題
If you want to change, don't accept the status quo!
如果你想要改變，你不能接受現狀！
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：楊易